Guide to the Isaac Hicks Papers 1791-1820 MS 297
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1791-1806; 18 Linear feet
  - Letters: 1801 A-C (Box -)
    - Letters: B (Except Barker; Bolton; Bunker), 1801 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Barker & Annesly; Robert Benson; Benson, Cropper & Benson; Joseph Bevin; and Richard Blow. There are multiple letters from Benson, Cropper & Benson regarding the formation of their company. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods. Other correspondence is in regard to the payment of debts. One letter discusses how the ship Sarah was detained by the Spanish Armada. The letter also discusses a treaty between the United States and the new French Republic. A letter is included in French.
      Ships Mentioned: Venus, Allion, Nancy, Sarah
    - Letters: Barker, 1801 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients with the surname Barker including James Barker, Jacob Barker, and Peter Barker. Jacob Barker discusses a law suit that has been brought against him. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the shipment of goods, particularly on the ship Venus.
      Ships Mentioned: Lydia, Venus
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (1), 1801 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Robert & John Bolton. The correspondence is predominantly in regards to regular business matters—mostly the sale and shipment of goods and the payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: Eliza
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (2), 1801 (Box 20, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Robert & John Bolton. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods such as glass, bran, bacon, building stone, and tobacco, as well as the payment of bills. They also write regarding the death of Captain John Dowall who died charging a cannon. Ships Mentioned: Recourse, Betsey, Diana, Venus, General Mercer
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (3), 1801 (Box 20, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Robert & John Bolton. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods such as feather beds, a church bell, and cotton. They also ask Hicks about his thoughts of a voyage to Russia, and an illness that John Bolton was fighting. They discuss the payment of bills and the procurement of insurance as well.
      Ships Mentioned: Thomas & Robert, General Mercer, Diana, George, Eliza, Nixon
    - Letters: Bunker, 1801 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients with the surname Bunker including David Bunker, Reuben Bunker, Solomon Bunker, and William Bunker. David Bunker discusses the weather and the transportation of goods, though no specific ship is mentioned. Reuben Bunker discusses his safe passage to 'Rodes'. Solomon Bunker discusses his trip from New York to Bristol, and discusses how they are hard pressed for provisions, stating that they are "all most in a state of starvation" until the harvest is in. William Bunker discusses his voyage to Bristol, as well as the procurement of goods such as salt.
      Ships Mentioned: Olive Branch, Mary, Warren
    - Letters: C (Except Coffin; Cropper & Benson), 1801 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including David Callaghan, John & Robert Chapman, Abiel Cheney, and Joseph Clements, among others. David Callaghan asks Hicks if he knows of any goods that can be shipped when the Commerce enters port. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton from Georgia, linens and wool, and iron. Other correspondence is in regards to bills of sale or the procurement of insurance.
      Ships Mentioned: Commerce, Mary, Aspasia, Mannila, Lydia
    - Letters: Coffin, 1801 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients with the surname Coffin including Alex Coffin Jr., Ann Coffin, Elihu Coffin, and Mark Coffin. Alex Coffin Jr. discusses an illness that he is fighting and how he has not been out of doors for some time due to it. He also asks Hicks to procure insurance for the General Mercer and to forward multiple letters to Bombay. Ann Coffin corresponds with Hicks regarding the payment of bills. Joshua Coffin discusses an outbreak of smallpox.
      Ships Mentioned: General Mercer, Washington, Jane, Mercury, Hero
    - Letters: Cropper & Benson, 1801 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Cropper & Benson. Main topics include prices current, as well as the sale and shipment of goods such as grain, tobacco, salt, coal, and flour. They discuss how the King of Prussia has prohibited the further export of grain in order to control the prices of grain and flour. They also discuss how prices of goods are expected to be cheaper in Baltimore and Philadelphia. They mention the death of the Emperor of Prussia and a peace treaty signed between England and France, and they discuss the effect that these events will have on the politics of Europe.
      Ships Mentioned: Albion, Commerce, Warren
  - Letters: 1801 D-H (Box -)
    - Letters: D (Except Deaves), 1801 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Davenport, and The Brothers DeBauque. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as the payment of bills. One letter is in French.
    - Letters: Deaves, Henry, 1801 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Henry Deaves. Main topics include problems with selling goods, prices current, the procurement of insurance, and the shipment of goods. Included are lists of shipments and drafts, and estimates of account information. Also included are copies of letters to Henry Deaves from other individuals such as Cropper & Benson and William English. It appears as if Deaves gave Hicks his correspondence, as nothing asks Hicks to forward the correspondence.
      Ships Mentioned: Mariner, Benjamin, Diana, Elias, Polly, Mercury, Edward, General Mercer
    - Letters: E, 1801 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including William Eaton and Nathaniel Emmons. A majority of the correspondence has to do with using Hicks as an intermediary for forwarding letters.
    - Letters: F (Except Fisher, Samuel & Meirs; Forbes, Edward; Fort, Edwin), 1801 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Joshua Fisher, William Fothergill, and Samuel Fulton. Joshua Fisher predominantly discusses the payment of bills and the procurement of insurance. William Fothergill discusses the sale of tobacco, corn, rye, and other dry goods. Robert Fry asks Hicks if he is able to sell any red or yellow flannel in the New York market.
      Ships Mentioned: Betsey, Hunter, Nixon, Sally
    - Letters: Fisher, Samuel & Meirs, 1801 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Samuel & Meirs Fisher. Main topics include the procurement and payment of insurance premiums, the sale and shipment of goods, and the settling of debts. They discuss how the Apollo was condemned in Santa Cruz and sold, as well as an accident that the ship was involved in. They discuss political bills going through Congress. They also inquire about ships potentially sailing for Dublin.
      Ships Mentioned: Apollo, Mary, Harmony
    - Letters: Forbes, Edward, 1801 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Edward Forbes. Main topics include interest on American stocks and the balancing of accounts. Forbes discusses political issues in Europe, especially regarding relations between France and Germany. He also discusses the selling price of goods such as flour and indian corn in Dublin, and how Hicks should avoid sending these goods as they will most likely be sold at a loss.
      Ships Mentioned: Adventure, Venus
    - Letters: Fort, Edwin, 1801 (Box 21, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Edwin Fort. Fort expresses regret at the fact that he was unable to fill an order Hicks placed. He later requests a vessel to ship goods. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods such as flour and tobacco.
      Ships Mentioned: Charles Curtis, Dorothy, Hampton
    - Letters: G, 1801 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Albert Gardner, Gideon & Albert Gardner, Gardner & Downer, Gardner & Mitchell, Samuel Gaskell, and Thomas Gelfin. Main topics include the sale and shipment of goods, predominantly whale products, flour, and linens; the payment of bills; and the procurement of insurance. Also included are invoices of goods shipped.
      Ships Mentioned: Perseverance, Hudson, Nancy, Friendship, Lucretia, General Mercer, Venus
    - Letters: H (Except Halliday; Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey; Hazard: Hilms; Howland), 1801 (Box 21, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Robert Hamilton, Hannay & Logan, Harvey & Fisher, Rowland Hazard, Richard Hughes, and George Hussey. Robert Hamilton expresses his satisfaction with Hicks in regards to orders that Hamilton placed. He also expresses his gratitude at the treatment he got from Hicks. Included are multiple Prices Current from the Liverpool area from Hannay & Logan. Along with the Prices Current, Hannay & Logan discuss the changing prices of goods. Harvey & Fisher introduce Hicks to potential new associates.
      Ships Mentioned:Peggy, President, Sarah, Dispatch, Mary, Sally, Betsey, Independence
  - Letters: 1801 Halliday-M (Box -)
    - Letters: Halliday, 1801 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Alexander Halliday. Halliday discusses his voyages, his debt, and the sale and shipment of goods. He thanks Hicks for forwarding his letters, requests financial advances, and discusses other financial matters. He also tells Hicks that he was "very sorry to hear that the Fever had become so alarming in New York that you had been obliged to quit the City."
      Ships Mentioned: Diana, Eliza, Ceres, George, Neptune, Sarah, Venus, Debbe
    - Letters: Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey, 1801 (Box 22, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey. They discuss the buying and selling of goods such as flaxseed, cotton, and tobacco. They talk about how cotton is not selling well and how rice had met a good market. They introduce new associates, and discuss the payment of bills and other financial matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Venus, Eliza
    - Letters: Hazard, Thomas Jr.; Holms; Howland, 1801 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients including Thomas Hazard, Jr. It also includes correspondence from David Holms and individuals with the surname Howland, including Isaac Howland and Sons, and John Howland. Thomas Hazard discusses how ships entering San Sebastian must be quarantined for 40 days. A large number of his letters discuss the ship Sarah and information having to do with the papers that go along with said ship. He asks Hicks to apologize to Joshua Sands for an error on Hazard's part regarding payment for services. David Holms tells Hicks that he got his name from Robert Bolton, and if he was in want of anything he should contact Hicks. He complains about his boarding situation, stating "small boys…are very noisy, and what is worse Mr. Everets has not command over them…and it was impossible for one to study." He also asks Hicks to send money so that Holms can pay his debts. Isaac Howland and Sons discuss the sale of two tons of Hemp and payment of bills.
      Ships Mentioned: Sarah, Lydia, Commerce, Fame, Lucretia
    - Letters: I-J, 1801 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Roza Ilizia, E. Jackson, Jonathan Jenkins, Robert Jenkins, and Silas Jones. Roza Ilizia is extremely concerned about her son, and sends Power of Attorney to Hicks. Phineas Janney discusses the purchase, shipment, and sale of flour and hopes that "The sale may prove easy & be a means of opening a correspondence that may be mutually advantageous." Jonathan Jenkins discusses trips to Jamaica and the West Indies. Robert Jenkins requests information on the price of insurance against capture by the Algerians. He also requests information about bills of sale.
      Ships Mentioned: Commerce, Sally, Betsey, American Hero, Allegany
    - Letters: K-L, 1801 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Jacob Klady, Lamb & Younger, and George Langtry. Jacob Klady discusses how the making of 20,000 tiles depends on the weather, and then continues to write about the status of said tiles. B. Lagrave leaves instructions for Hicks regarding shipping goods, collecting payments, and requesting information. He also writes to Hicks about purchasing flour from New Orleans. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the sale and shipment of goods, and other regular business matters. Also included is correspondence in French.
      Ships Mentioned: Perseverance, Debby, John, Eagle
    - Letters: M (Except Macy; Mellish; Moores; Morgan & Douglass), 1801 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including William Malure & Co., George McConnell, A. McGown, Joseph Machin, Jacob Mark, Joseph Morris, and Henry Oliver & Sons. A majority of the correspondence has to do with regular business matters such as the sale and shipment of goods. Also included are letters to Jacob Mark from Rathbone, Hughes & Duncan.
      Ships Mentioned: Olive Branch, Exchange, Recovery, Laurel
  - Letters: 1801 Macy-R (Box -)
    - Letters: Macy; Mellish, 1801 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from clients with the surname Macy and Mellish, including Seth Macy, S & O Macy, and J & W Mellish & Co. Seth Macy discusses issues he found with interest that he had been charged as well as the payment of other bills. J & W Mellish & Co predominantly discuss the payment of bills. There are also multiple duplicates.
      Ships Mentioned: Olive Branch, Laura
    - Letters: Moores; Morgan & Douglass, 1801 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Reuben Moores and Morgan & Douglass. Reuben Moores primarily discusses the sale and shipment of goods, though he does not specify what goods. He also talks about some issues he had with a voyage and a ship taking on water. He states though, that he does not think that the ship had any major damage. Morgan & Douglass primarily discuss accounts payable and other financial information. They also discuss the sale and shipment of sugar.
      Ships Mentioned: Mercury, Allegany, General Washington, John Adams, America
    - Letters: P (Except Potts; Prudhomme), 1801 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Judah Paddock, Stephen Paddock, Jonathan Parker, William Philips, and William Prescod & Co. Judah Paddock discusses the sale and shipment of goods such as salt, fabric, wheat, and coal. He also discusses the events of a voyage he took. Jonathan Parker discusses damages that one of his ships took and proceeded to ask for information about insurance. William Philips discusses the shipment of books and difficulties he has had procuring some titles.
      Ships Mentioned: Allegany, General Mercer, Oswego
    - Letters: Potts; Prudhomme, 1801 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from individuals with the surname Potts and Prudhomme, including John Potts, Thomas Potts, and L. Prudhomme. Thomas Potts asks Hicks to forward a package to Potts's father who was going to be passing through New York. Potts also thanks Hicks for taking responsibility for Potts's son, John, and putting him in a good school. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the shipping of goods and the settling of accounts.
      Ships Mentioned: Eliza, William, Henry
    - Letters: R (Except Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan; Rocquette-Beeldemaker G; Rodman; Rotch), 1801 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Paul Ray, Rhodes & Briggs, Samuel Rhodes, and John Robinson & Sons. Rhodes & Briggs discuss the turn of the market in regards to flaxseed and oat meal. They also discuss pricing, and how the prices goods have fetched did not meet their expectations. Samuel Rhodes discusses how a ship bound for Havana was inspected by two British war ships. John Robinson & Sons predominantly discuss the shipment of flour and the settling of accounts.
      Ships Mentioned: John, Molly, Commerce, Nancy, Sarah, General Mercer
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (1), 1801 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They discuss how Captain Paddock is taking on cabin passengers for one of his ships. They discuss the changing price of produce. Also included is mention of Preliminary Articles of Peace between England and France. Main topics include the settling of accounts and the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton, tobacco, iron, staves, indigo, flaxseed, and more. One letter discusses the Brown Bread Bill, which dictated the grain of flour that could be used for bread.
      Ships Mentioned: Diana, Allegany, General Mercer, Hazard
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (2), 1801 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. Included is a copy of the Preliminary Articles of Peace between Great Britain and France as well as a summary of said articles. They discuss the changing prices of cotton and American produce, and other goods such as tobacco. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to regular business matters such as the sale and shipment of goods, the payment of bills, and the schedule by which ships are sailing. They also discuss bringing about a lawsuit in order to recover property based on not being paid money they were owed.
      Ships Mentioned: Diana, Union, Portland, Allegany, General Mercer, Washington
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (3), 1801 (Box 23, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the shipment of goods and mainly focuses on the schedule with which ships are sailing and the sale of goods such as cotton and tobacco. There is also a printed letter regarding the bounties on American flour.
      Ships Mentioned: Perseverance, Galen, General Mercer, Liberty, Allegany, Ocean
    - Letters: Rocquette-Beeldemaker. G; Rodman; Rotch, 1801 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      : This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Rocquette-Beeldemaker. G, and clients with the surname Rodman and Rotch, including Samuel Rodman, Thomas Rodman, Benjamin Rotch, Thomas Rotch, and William Rotch. Rocquette & Beeldemaker discuss an impending peace between Germany and France and the treaty that was signed. They also discuss pricing quite often. Samuel Rodman discusses the sale of whale products and the payment of bills. William Rotch mostly discusses the payment of bills and other regular business matters.
  - Letters: 1801 S-W (Box -)
    - Letters: S-Sk, 1801 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Charles O. Sereven, George Shaw, J. Shearman, Isaac Sherman, Allen Shepherd, William Shotwell, and Peter Siemsen & Company. Isaac Sherman discusses admitting an unidentified child to a school. He also discusses finances with Hicks. Peter Siemsen discusses the sale and shipment of goods such as cotton. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as handling payments and selling goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Olympus, Commerce
    - Letters: Sk-Sw (Except Spear, Robert), 1801 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Thomas Slade, George Smith & Co., Thomas Stewardson, and Thomas Sturge. Thomas Slade discusses having Hicks purchase products for him such as sugar and linens. Samuel Slee asks for information about his wife. George Smith discusses multiple ships and their goods, such as coffee, sugar, linen, and cotton. Smith also discusses the payment and receipt of bills. Thomas Sturge discusses the sale of wheat and flour.
      Ships Mentioned: General Mercer, Ann, Pennsylvania, Commerce, Elizabeth, Molly, Thomas
    - Letters: Spear, Robert, 1801 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Robert Spear. He talks in depth about the cotton market in England. He also discusses how he has a favorable opinion of joining Hicks in a dry goods endeavor. He brings up how politics have been making trade difficult, especially in Hamburg. There are multiple duplicates included.
      Ships Mentioned: General Mercer
    - Letters: T, 1801 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Taber & Sons, Loring Taber, and Daniel Tucker. Loring Taber discusses one of his voyages, and how poor weather made his journey difficult. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
    - Letters: W, 1801 (Box 24, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Joseph Wales, Peter P. Walter, J. Warden, Daniel Waterman, and Richard Wheatley. Peter Walter discusses insurance policies on goods from Havana, Cuba. Daniel Waterman discusses the difficulties with selling goods. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as the buying and selling of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Beaver, Hercules, Olive Branch, Perseverance, Joseph Harvey
  - Letters: 1802 A-G (Box -)
    - Letters: A-B (Except Benson, Cropper & Benson; Bevan; Bolton, John & Robert), 1802 (Box 25, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Rufus Barkus, Richard Blow, William Bolton, Andrew Browne, and John Bulkeley. The correspondence is predominantly in regards to regular business matters, especially the sale of goods such as Irish Linens. John Bulkeley discusses being paid in plundered Italian goods in one letter, and in another he discusses a ship being seized in Brazil.
      Ships Mentioned: Jane, Nancy
    - Letters: Benson, Cropper, & Benson, 1802 (Box 25, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Benson, Cropper & Benson. Main topics include the purchasing of insurance, the sale and shipment of goods-especially cotton and rice, paying duties, the weather, and the harvest in Great Britain.
      Ships Mentioned: Delight, Isabella, Albion, Mars
    - Letters: Bevan, 1802 (Box 25, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Joseph Bevan. Main topics include the procurement of insurance, the payment of bills, invoices, and the sale and shipment of goods-especially rice and cotton.
      Ships Mentioned: Susan